A banker in London sends the latest stock info
to his colleagues /ˈkɒliːɡ/ in Hong Kong in less than a second.
With a single click, a customer in New York
orders electronics made in Beijing,
transported across the ocean within days
by cargo plane or container ship.
The speed and volume /ˈvɒljuːm 大量/ at which goods and information
move across the world today is unprecedented /ˈprɛsɪdənt 先例；惯例/ in history.
But global exchange itself is older than we think,
reaching back over 2,000 years along a 5,000 mile stretch /strɛtʃ 延伸/
known as the Silk Road.
The Silk Road wasn't actually a single road,
but a network of multiple /ˈmʌltɪpəl/ routes
that gradually /grædʒuəli 渐渐地/ emerged over centuries,
connecting to various settlements and to each other
thread by thread.
The first agricultural civilizations were isolated places
in fertile /ˈfɜːtaɪl 肥沃的/ river valleys /ˈvælɪ 山谷 溪谷/,
their travel impeded /ɪmˈpiːd  阻碍/ by surrounding geography /dʒɪˈɒɡrəfɪ/
and fear of the unknown.
But as they grew,
they found that the arid /ˈærɪd 干旱的/ deserts and steps on their borders
were inhabited /ɪnˈhæbɪt 栖息/, not by the demons /ˈdiːmən 恶魔/ of folklore /ˈfəʊkˌlɔː 民间传说/,
but nomadic /nəʊˈmædɪk 游牧的/ tribes /traɪb 部落/ on horseback.
The Scythians, who ranged from Hungary to Mongolia,
had come in contact with the civilizations of
Greece, Egypt, India and China.
These encounters were often less than peaceful.
But even through raids /reɪd 突袭；抢劫/ and warfare /ˈwɔːˌfɛə/,
as well as trade and protection of traveling merchants
in exchange for tariffs /tærif/,
the nomads /ˈnəʊmæd 游牧民/ began to spread goods, ideas and technologies
between cultures with no direct contact.
One of the most important strands /strænd 线,链/ of this growing web
was the Persian Royal Road,
completed by Darius the First in the 5th century BCE.
Stretching nearly 2,000 miles from the Tigris /ˈtaɪɡrɪs 底格里斯河/ River to the Aegean /iːˈdʒiːən 爱琴海/ Sea,
its regular relay /ˈriːleɪ  中继设备/ points allowed goods and messages
to travel at nearly 1/10 the time it would take a single traveler.
With Alexander /ˌælɪɡˈzɑːndə/ the Great's conquest /ˈkɒnkwest 征服/ of Persia,
and expansion into Central Asia through capturing cities like Samarkand,
and establishing new ones like Alexandria /ˌælɪɡˈzændrɪə/ Eschate,
the network of Greek, Egyptian /ɪˈdʒɪpʃən/, Persian and Indian culture and trade
extended farther east than ever before,
laying the foundations for a bridge between China and the West.
This was realized in the 2nd century BCE,
when an ambassador /æmˈbæsədə/ named Zhang Qian,
sent to negotiate with nomads /ˈnəʊmæd 游牧民/ in the West,
returned to the Han Emperor with tales /teɪl 传说/ of
sophisticated /səˈfɪstɪˌkeɪtɪd 老练的/ civilizations, prosperous /ˈprɒspərəs 繁荣的/ trade
and exotic /ɪɡˈzɒtɪk 异国的/ goods beyond the western borders.
Ambassadors /æmˈbæsədə/ and merchants were sent towards
Persia and India to trade silk and jade /dʒeɪd/ for horses and cotton,
along with armies to secure their passage /ˈpæsɪdʒ 通道/.
Eastern and western routes gradually linked together
into an integrated /ˈɪntɪˌɡreɪtɪd 整合的/ system spanning Eurasia /jʊəˈreɪʃə 欧亚大陆/,
enabling cultural and commercial exhange
farther than ever before.
Chinese goods made their way to Rome,
causing an outflow /ˈaʊtˌfləʊ 流出/ of gold that led to a ban on silk,
while Roman /ˈrəʊmən/ glassware was highly prized in China.
Military expeditions /ˌɛkspɪˈdɪʃən 远征.探险/ in Central Asia
also saw encounters between Chinese and Roman soldiers /ˈsəʊldʒə/.
Possibly even transmitting crossbow technology
to the Western world.
Demand for exotic /ɪɡˈzɒtɪk/ and foreign goods
and the profits they brought,
kept the strands /strænd 线/ of the Silk Road intact /ɪnˈtækt 完整无缺的/,
even as the Roman Empire disintegrated /dɪsˈɪntɪˌɡreɪt 分裂/
and Chinese dynasties rose and fell.
Even Mongolian hoards /hɔːd 贮藏/, known for pillage /ˈpɪlɪdʒ 掠夺/ and plunder /ˈplʌndə 抢劫/,
actively protected the trade routes, rather than disrupting them.
But along with commodities /kəˈmɒdɪtɪ 商品/, these routes also enabled
the movement of traditions, innovations, ideologies /ˌaɪdɪˈɒlədʒɪ 思想/ and languages.
Originating in India, Buddhism /ˈbʊdɪzəm 佛教/ migrated /maɪˈɡreɪt/ to China and Japan
to become the dominant religion there.
Islam /ˈɪzlɑːm/ spread from the Arabian /əˈreɪbɪən/ Peninsula /pɪˈnɪnsjʊlə/ into South Asia,
blending /blɛnd 混合/ with native beliefs
and leading to new faiths /feɪθ 信仰/, like Sikhism /ˈsiːkɪzəm 锡克教/.
And gunpowder made its way from China to the Middle East
forging /fɔːdʒ 锻造/ the futures of the Ottoman /ˈɒtəmən/, Safavid and Mughul Empires.
In a way, the Silk Road's success led to its own demise /dɪˈmaɪz 转让/
as new maritime /ˈmærɪˌtaɪm 海上的/ technologies, like the magnetic /mæɡˈnɛtɪk 有磁性的/ compass /ˈkʌmpəs 指南针/,
found their way to Europe, making long land routes obsolete /ˈɒbsəˌliːt 淘汰/.
Meanwhile, the collapse /kəˈlæps 倒塌/ of Mongol rule
was followed by China's withdrawal from international trade.
But even though the old routes and networks did not last,
they had changed the world forever
and there was no going back.
Europeans seeking new maritime /ˈmærɪˌtaɪm 海上的/ routes
to the riches they knew awaited in East Asia
led to the Age of Exploration /ˌɛkspləˈreɪʃən/
and expansion into Africa and the Americas.
Today, global interconnectedness shapes our lives like never before.
Canadian shoppers buy t-shirts made in Bangladesh /ˌbæŋɡləˈdeʃ 孟加拉国/,
Japanese audiences watch British television shows,
and Tunisians /tjuːˈnɪzɪən 突尼斯人/ use American software to launch a revolution.
The impact of globalization on culture and economy is indisputable /ˌɪndɪˈspjuːtəbəl 不容置疑的/.
But whatever its benefits and drawbacks /ˈdrɔːˌbæk 缺点/,
it is far from a new phenomenon.
And though the mountains, deserts and oceans
that once separated us
are now circumvented /ˌsɜːkəmˈvɛnt 规避/ through super sonic vehicles,
cross-continental /ˌkɒntɪˈnentəl/ communication cables,
and signals beamed through space
rather than caravans /ˈkærəˌvæn 旅行商队/ traveling for months,
none of it would have been possible
without the pioneering cultures
whose efforts created the Silk Road:
history's first world wide web.